Inventory of the Hubert Coslet Armstrong papers
Hoover Institution Archives
Hubert Coslet Armstrong papers
1918-1976
92027
Hoover Institution Archives
10 manuscript boxes (4.2 linear feet)
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, curricular materials, and printed matter relating to various aspects of education in the United States, educational programs in Japanese American internment camps during World War II, and postwar education in Japan.
Armstrong, Hubert Coslet, 1900-
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 1992.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the online catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
1900 June 22 Born, Lincoln, Nebraska
1921-1926 Member of United States National Guard
1926 Married first wife, Olive Dexter
1926-1929 Teacher, Pribiloff Islands, Alaska
1929-1931 Psychology teaching fellow, University of Washington, Seattle, Washington
1930-1931 BS and MS, University of Washington
1931-1934 Administrator and counselor, Oakland Public Schools, Oakland, California
1933 Summer lecturer, Mills College, Oakland, California
1933-1938 Researcher, Institute of Child Welfare, University of California, Berkeley
1935-1939 Broadcaster for the program Mindways, National Broadcasting Company, San Francisco, California
1941-1942 Teacher and specialist, Indian Service School, United States Office of Indian Services, Stewart, Nevada
1942 Specialist, Japanese War Relocation Center, Poston, Arizona
1944-1945 Research consultant, California State Reconstruction and Redevelopment Commission
1947-1948 Director of Research, Civil Information and Education Section, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Japan
1948 Advisor to the Minister of Education of the government in Korea, United States Department of the Army
1949 Research consultant, California State Assembly Commission on Public Education, California State Legislature
1949 Married second wife, Masago Shibuya
1949-1951 Professor, Harvard University Graduate School of Education, Cambridge, Massachusetts
1951-1953 Director, Public Education Association, New York, New York
1953 PhD, Stanford University, Stanford, California
1956-1957 Consultant, Department of Rehabilitation, Stanford University, Hawaii
1960-1961 Consultant and research fellow, University of Tokyo, Japan
1966-1971 Wrote "Charley Russel's Montana" (unpublished)
1978 Died, Los Angeles County, California
Scope and Content of Collection
Writings, correspondence, memoranda, reports, curricular materials, and printed matter relating to various aspects of education in the United States, educational programs and correspondence at the War Relocation Center at Poston, Arizona during World War II, articles about Japanese and Japanese-Americans at internment camps, and research on post-war education in Japan, as well as Armstrong's doctoral dissertation.
Arrangement Statement
Armstrong's original order and folder titles (where available) have been maintained. Where there was no prior arrangement, materials were alphabetized and arranged chronologically. Folder titles created by archivist are in brackets.
Education--United States.; Japanese Americans--Evacuation and relocation, 1942-1945.; World War, 1939-1945--United States.; World War, 1939-1945--Education and the war.; Education--Japan.; Japan--History--Allied occupation, 1945-1952.; Military government.; Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers. Civil Information and Education Section.
- Course materials: Language Development, 1940-1965 (Box-folder 1: 1)
- Course materials: Guidance, 1950-1956 (Box-folder 1: 2)
- Course materials: Case Method, 1940-1953 (Box-folder 1: 3)
- Case study: Selection of administrative candidates, Covina CA 1959, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 1: 4)
  Scope and Contents note
  A case study analysis and review for the Covina School District's Principal Selection Committee. Includes handbook for school officials, printed matter, and correspondence with the committee and the Educational Testing Service (ETS) of Princeton, New Jersey.
- Course materials: Research Design and Methodology, circa 1958-1964 (Box-folder 1: 5)
- Course materials: Brain Damage and Neurological Disorders, 1954-1955 (Box-folder 1: 6)
- California Governor's Conference on Education, 1955 (Box-folder 1: 7)
- Research Project on Post-War Education in Japan, U of Tokyo 1960-1, 1945-1961 (Box-folder 2: 1-5)
  Includes translation of "Onna Daigaku," notes, letters, final report to Mr. Coladarci on Japan, and materials on the Ikeda-Robertson issue.
- Micellaneous materials to 1929, 1926-1930 (Box-folder 3: 1)
  Includes papers, graded tests, and illustrations of the human brain.
- Ancedotes, writings, thoughts, 1933-1976 (Box-folder 3: 2)
- Biographical materials, 1938-1965 (Box-folder 3: 3)
  Includes: American Men of Science: The Social and Behavioral Sciences, 10th ed., 1962; Who's Who in American Education, Vol. 16, 1953-1954; and Who's Who in the West, 9th ed., 1965-1966.
- Original ["Charley Russall's Montana"], 1970-1971 (Box-folder 3: 4)
- Montana ["Charlie Russell's Montana," typed manuscripts], circa 1971 (Box-folder 3: 5)
- Oakland (CA) Public Schools 1931-1945, 1931-1953 (Box-folder 4: 1-2)
- Poston (AZ) War Relocation Authority 1942-3, 1941-1944 (Box-folder 4: 3-4, Box-folder 5: 1)
  Also includes United States Department of Interior, Office [Bureau] of Indian Affairs files.
- California State Department of Education 1945-6, 1944-1946 (Box-folder 5: 2)
- Dir Res, CI&E, GHQ, SCAP, Tokyo, Japan, 1946-1947 (Box-folder 5: 3)
  Director of Research files, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Civil Information and Education Section.
- Harvard University School of Education, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 5: 4)
- Dir., Public Education Association, New York City 1951-3, 1950-1953 (Box-folder 5: 5)
- Claremont Graduate School, Claremont, CA, 1953-1965 (Box-folder 5: 6)
  Includes materials on California Commission on Public School Administration.
- Radio broadcasts, 1936-1939
  Indices of broadcasts, with date aired, the title of the program, and the age of the case study on topic. Includes transcripts of radio broadcasts of Hubert R. Stolz, M.D. from 1932 to 1934 and later Hubert Coslet Armstrong from 1934 to 1939 on the National Broadcasting Company radio network broadcast over stations KGO and KLX. The radio show Mindways was written and produced by Armstrong, covering human behavior and featuring stories on parenting, education, child growth, and development issues. Some episodes cover topics such as thumb sucking, fighting, adolescence, left-handed children, and exceptional children.
  - 1932 October 25-1933 October 30 (Box-folder 6: 1)
  - 1933 November 27-1934 June 14 (Box-folder 6: 2)
  - 1934 July 28-1934 December 21 (Box-folder 6: 3)
  - 1935 January 11-1935 June 21 (Box-folder 6: 4)
  - 1935 July 19-1935 December 27 (Box-folder 6: 5)
  - 1936 January 10-1936 June 12 (Box-folder 6: 6)
  - 1936 July 3-1936 December 18 (Box-folder 6: 7)
  - 1937 January 1-1937 June 18 (Box-folder 6: 8)
  - 1937 July 2-1939 November 25 (Box-folder 6: 9)
  - [Radio broadcast research materials, correspondence, and transcripts], 1935-1939 (Box-folder 7: 1)
- [Japanese Ministry of Education and other agency publications], 1949-1959 (Box-folder 7: 2)
- [Armstrong article printed in Japanese], 1961 (Box-folder 7: 3)
- [ Education in the New Japan, Vol. 1, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Civil Information & Education Section, Education Division], 1948 May (Box 7)
- [ Education in the New Japan, Vol. 2 and appendix, General Headquarters, Supreme Commander for the Allied Powers, Civil Information & Education Section, Education Division], 1948 May (Box 7)
- Miscellaneous writings, 1949-1953 (Box-folder 8: 1)
- [Article drafts, and New York experiences], 1943-1959 (Box-folder 8: 2)
- [Article drafts and hospital experiences], 1950-1966 (Box-folder 8: 3)
- [Articles for publication with correspondence and printed matter], 1955-1971 (Box-folder 8: 4)
- [Miscellaneous printed matter on Japan], 1942-1959 (Box-folder 8: 5)
- [Clippings from Hawaii, Sacramento, Los Angeles, and New York publications], 1951-1962 (Box-folder 8: 6)
  Includes articles by and about Armstrong.
- [Armstrong, Hubert Coslet, "The Relationship of the Auditory and Visual Vocabularies of Children," PhD dissertation, School of Education, Stanford University], 1953 (Box 8)
- [Correspondence], 1918-1967
  - [Armstrong family], 1925-1946 (Box-folder 9: 1)
  - [Mr. and Mrs. Andrew J. Armstrong], 1918-1949 (Box-folder 9: 2-3)
  - [Mr. Hubert C. Armstrong, Jr.], 1930-1956 (Box-folder 9: 4)
  - [Mrs. Hubert C. (Olive) Armstrong], 1930-1955 (Box-folder 9: 5)
  - [Mr. and Mrs. Philip C. Armstrong], 1926-1967 (Box-folder 9: 6)
  - [Mr. and Mrs. Earl E. Hetrick], 1923-1949 (Box-folder 9: 7)
  - [Dexter family], 1929-1945 (Box-folder 9: 8)
  - [General], 1918-1945 (Box-folder 10: 1)
  - [Friends], 1920-1944 (Box-folder 10: 2)
  - [Miscellaneous notes from others], circa 1928 (Box-folder 10: 3)
  - [Professional], 1929-1954 (Box-folder 10: 4)
  - [University of Washington and Mills College], 1927-1942 (Box-folder 10: 5)
  - [California Teachers' Association and "Ham and Eggs" pension retirement], 1938-1939 (Box-folder 10: 6)
- [Ephemera, memorabilia, and pamphlets], 1924-1954 (Box-folder 10: 7)
- [Clippings and printed matter], 1940-1951 (Box-folder 10: 8)